<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Liuw's Thinkpad</title><link href="http://blog.liuw.name/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.liuw.name/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.liuw.name/</id><updated>2015-11-16T22:30:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Free Software is not Free</title><link href="http://blog.liuw.name/free-software-is-not-free.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-16T22:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei Liu</name></author><id>tag:blog.liuw.name,2015-11-16:free-software-is-not-free.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There has been some back and forth discussion on how Xen's security process
sucks. Well, not quite. Though the email was titled that way, the content
didn't have much to do with security process per se. True, there are
technically correct points in that thread (with which I completely agree), but
the underlying theme is disturbing. That thread prompted me into thinking how
open source project functions. What I'm going to dwell on is not Xen project
specific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, there are people that don't want to invest time and money into an
open source project but want undue influence. The cold hard fact is that things
just don't work that way. Making a piece of software requires a lot of work.
Whatever great idea floating around needs to be implemented by an actual person
-- that comes down to time and money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So while open source projects are often branded as "free" (as in either free
speech or free beer), the work behind them is not.  Open source world nowadays
function differently than 20 years ago. It has developed into a business model
that every major project has some vested interest of some companies. Their
employees act in the interest of the employers and prioritise work items
accordingly. There are hobbyists working on a project but it's hard for them to
make substantive contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have expectation that, since open source project is "free", they are
entitled to add more work items even if they don't want to invest time and
money. This is fundamentally wrong. Well, they are "free" to voice their
opinions, but then developers are "free" to ignore part of or all of those
opinions. The door is always open for collaborations though -- everybody is
"free" to join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a proprietary software world, there is normally no public channel to ask for
changes. But I'm pretty sure it all comes down to support contract or whatnot.
I can't imagine someone out of the blue goes to Microsoft and says "the way you
work is wrong, your priority is wrong, let me tell you what to do, but I don't
want to pay you anything".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I have to admit I sometimes feel upset for such attitude and entitlement.
The joy of working on open source project is ruined. Not respecting the effort
other people put into the project is just demotivating. And I'm not only
talking about myself or Xen project specifically. There have been several
instances of developer burnout. Many people also wrote essays on similar
subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my humble opinion, free software projects are just not "free" as some people
would like them to be. Ultimately, a free software project is what the whole
community makes it.  If one disagrees on the direction of a project, he or she
should join and lead the change for the better.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Of Course Joanna is Right</title><link href="http://blog.liuw.name/of-course-joanna-is-right.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-01T14:50:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei Liu</name></author><id>tag:blog.liuw.name,2015-11-01:of-course-joanna-is-right.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There have been quite a lot of Xen-bashing for XSA-148. It's no doubt a cluster-fuck, a reflection of the sad state of the art of computer system security. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Ian pointed out in his blog post, we collectively choose features over security. Security only matters when there is a big fuck-up like HeartBleed, ShellShock or XSA-148.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is even sadder is the attitude of media in general. Journalists actively hunt for headline-worth bugs. With the help of slightly technically incorrect writing that skews the true situation and some other implications along the way, they have many masterpieces that conclude the dismal state of computer system security. Not that they're wrong about the conclusion, just in my opinion they completely miss the important points. Remember VENOM? I didn't mention it in my list of big fuck-ups because it really wasn't anything serious except for its cool name. But media picked on that and started a spree nonetheless, just because the cool name fit right in their headline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's wrong with the world? In short, we really really really don't care about security. The effort of a small group of people pales in front of the a world that cares more about cool new shiny things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my world view, this is a ever changing world. Software is under constant pressure to evolve to adapt to external environment. No software is perfect. There were, are and going to be major bugs in all seriously written software. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one thinks a piece of software is secure just because there is no public security advisories list, then he or she is delusional. Good luck with building things on top of that piece of software without investing significant amount of money performing security audit. And if the media picks on a piece of software because there is such a list, they are actually doing a disservice to the wider community. That drives projects to sweep problems under the carpet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back to XSA-148, there is no excuse on Xen project's part. That's a serious bug, period. What should be done next is to use the correct process to avoid such error again, and in similar situation, minimise the impact. Xen community constantly work on procedural improvements, learn from the past and make the future better. A constructive way of moving forward is for Xen community to engage with security researchers to improve the security of Xen. I look forward to that.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>On Toxicity on LKML</title><link href="http://blog.liuw.name/on-toxicity-on-lkml.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-10-18T23:50:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Wei Liu</name></author><id>tag:blog.liuw.name,2015-10-18:on-toxicity-on-lkml.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sarah Sharp quit, publicly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to be clear: I don't know her personally. The closest link she and I ever had was that I participated in Outreachy (formally known as Outreach Program for Women) as a mentor, where she had been one of the coordinators for some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do, however, have a lot of sympathy for her. And I would say I agree, to some degree, what she said in her blog post. The toxicity on LKML is appalling. Luckily I wasn’t on the receiving end of any of those, but even as a bystander I felt it was too much every time I saw crude rudeness. In short, LKML never ceased to amaze me on the level of rudeness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it becomes increasingly clear to me that many LKML users (not necessarily Linux kernel developers) are seeing rudeness as necessity to ensure code quality. If you don’t believe me, just look at comment section under Sarah's story on LWN.net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I firmly believe that an open source community should be blunt to technical issues but respectful to people. I use that as my guideline to deal with people in my day to day work. As someone who has been making a living by contributing to a number of open source projects, I start to question whether it is worth putting more effort in Linux kernel development. But then I realise I’ve already been retreating from Linux kernel development long time ago. The decision was made subconsciously without me even noticing it. Of course I still work on it when I’m paid to do so, but other than that, I don’t think I will spend my spare time on it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The CAPTCHA Economy</title><link href="http://blog.liuw.name/the-captcha-economy.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-17T10:50:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Wei Liu</name></author><id>tag:blog.liuw.name,2014-05-17:the-captcha-economy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;During daily lunch time chat yesterday in the office kitchen, my friend told me about a service he has been using for a while. And that provoked me to look further into this and discovered some interesting facts. Though not all of my questions about that service have been answered (either by him or my own investigation), I would still like to write down my thought so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service in question is a kind of service that use human power to recognise CAPTCHA images. As a client, you go to a website, register, top up some credit, then invoke their API to send images and get back results. Those CAPTCHA images are distributed to workers around the globe, then text result returned. There is a bidding system in place. If request volume is high then the price goes up, otherwise it goes down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend told me about one particular site he's using, but he also mentioned that there's tons of similar sites on the Internet. The service is charged at per request basis. The average cost for hiring someone behind a computer to recognise one image is about 1.5 cents. My friend told me that he paid $10 one year ago and he still had $7 credit when we had the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kind of think of this kind of service a clever hack to leverage machine power (to distribute and collect) and human power (to recognise patterns) to achieve certain goal. However, what's astonishing is that the average cost is so low that I don't even understand how this system manage to sustain itself. I mean, are those workers really get paid enough to feed themselves? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually opened that site my friend is using when I got home. What's handy is that it shows various stats for its service. I can see, with the bidding system in place, the price for 1000 requests goes from $0.75 to $1.5. Most of the time the price stays around $1. That is, in my opinion, still too low. However I'm certainly wrong because this system seems to work fine. The site states it has been in business since 2007. Further down the site there is a pretty pie chart showing the distribution of workers worldwide. High on the top are Pakistan, India, Indonesia, Vietnam etc, which consist of more than 70% of all workers. China is also on the list with a number of ~3%. Interestingly USA is also on the pie chart, and it has more or less the same percentage of China. Russian and Ukrainian workers are also non-neglectable. The number of workers tops at 1000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend and I did some back-of-the-envelope calculation on the revenue of this service. Unfortunately I didn't take note about it so I'm here to do it again, from scratch. According to the material on the website, the average time to recognise an image is 15 seconds. But we decided to make it 10 seconds, given our own experience dealing with CAPTCHA images. So, for an average person like my friend and me, he can probably finish 6 requests per minute. That makes 360 requests per hour. Multiple that by 1000 (the maximum number of workers seen on the website from previous day's data), then divide that by 1000 (the average price for 1000 requests was $1). That yields the result of the maximum possible hourly revenue of that service, that is, $360/h. We had no idea the percentage that the service provider takes. If it is 10%, that makes it $60/h. I think that's probably enough to sustain the cost of maintenance, bandwidth etc, even enough to make small profit out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might be profitable from service provider's point of view, but I still cannot see how feasible it is for a worker to make a living out of it. I also told another friend about this service and had a short discussion. Her idea is that probably the workers are not treating it as a full time job. But my point stands still, it's not profitable for a worker because you need a computer and Internet connection to do that job. The payback is not even likely to cover the expense, let alone make a profit / living out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could be wrong, so I decided to go further. There's a line of text of much smaller font size saying "if you want to do data entry job, click here". I clicked that link, another website popped up. A remarkable line from the new website showed that the price can be as low as $0.35 per 1000 entries. I couldn't help asking myself how would anyone want to do this. Nonetheless I registered an worker account (with a newly registered email of course) and logged in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interface is quite simple. The first page is "workspace", where you can look at the image you receive and enter text. For every image you receive there is a count down timer at the bottom, if you don't type at all during that time, the timer goes down. Presumably if the timer goes to zero the image is dispatched to other worker. But if you type anything, the timer is "refilled".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I entered a few entries. Suddenly my work item was revoked and website told me that I entered one thing wrong -- well, I didn't pay much attention for sure. I was told that if I make 5 mistakes in a month my account will be banned. That's quite scary, given the amount of work you required to do to make so little (1000 entries for $1) and the mistakes you're allowed to make (5 per month). Apparently the dispatch queue was not so full because I idled for once or twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I soon lost my interest in this game and turned to look at the navigation bar. I saw several tabs, among which was "payment". Also there's a "score board"-ish tab. I also given that account to my friend. She kind of found it interesting and looked at it as a game. However, I would doubt if anyone who wants to make money from it enjoys this as much as my friend did. When I got that account back, the system refreshed my payment. I could see that my friend and I entered 26 entries and made $0.013. Well, that's only $0.005 per entry!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a look at the "score board". Top 1 worker made ~$180 last month, while number 100 made ~$42.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After playing with the system and seeing the "score board", I had the impression that this is not an appealing job for me. I mean, even if someone is in desperate need of money, he or she should not consider doing this, because I don't see possible way to make any money out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely I don't know enough about other Asian countries, I don't really have an idea what their life standard is like. So probably for those countries high on the list, their workers can actually make profit from this job. As for USA workers, I have a theory that they might be homeless with laptop, and have access to free electricity and free wifi -- I've seen report on this lifestyle, they get free laptop from recycling station / donation and free electricity / wifi from McDonald. To be honest, the life standard of USA homeless is quite high compared to other countries, so that they can probably use this system to earn themselves a cup of coffee when they have nothing else to do. But I don't think those USA workers rely on this system to make a living by any means. For the developing countries, the device required to go into this job, the Internet connection and the electricity are not free (not saying that there's no free ride at all, just not as easy to get as in the US).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wearing my Chinese hat on, I can say more specific thing. Say I'm a guy from a very small town (by Chinese standard of course) and want to go into this job, I will first need a computer, which needs to be at the very least able to run an graphical desktop environment and a web browser. That will probably cost me 500 Yuan (~$80) if I buy a very very very old second hand computer. Then the Internet connection will probably cost me 30 Yuan (~$5) per month. Assume the power of my computer 200W, working 8 hours per day, unit price per watt 0.6 Yuan (~$0.1), that makes the electricity bill ~1 Yuan (~$0.16) per day. To cover the electricity bill alone, I will need to enter 160 entries. To cover the Internet fee I will need to enter 50000 entries. So, just to cover regular expenses, I will need to enter 5000 + 160 * 30 = 9800 entries (30 is the number of working days, and yes, I consider myself workaholic). To get back my investment on computer I will need to enter another 80000 entries. After all that, I get a job with hourly rate of 2.27 Yuan ($0.36), which is can barely feed myself given the current household level in my hometown. But of course, if I really have nothing else to do, this job is still something to get myself occupied -- any income is better than no income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I don't think as a worker it is worthy at all to do this job. However this kind of service exists, however small it is (the said service provider has 1000 workers top). I don't understand why. Probably there's poverty that's way beyond my understanding, probably workers never take on it as sole income source. I would put my bet on the latter.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>